[Music]
Okay. Uh over the so I don't know in
1993 or something like that I started uh
ACI uh with some other friends and uh we
did I said I would do 18 courses. It
took seven years and that covers the
highlights of the gish course and uh I I
was had just I finished my gish in 95 so
I was excited to do it and I was I
really wanted to share
it. Am I supposed to speak for
translators
Tim?
Okay. Uh, so I was excited to share it
and and um and I I was working more than
full-time and I was doing a class every
night, most nights and then
uh you know it got it got more and more
deep and then uh I was going to start my
three-year retreat and uh my students
asked me uh would I teach Diamond Way
afterwards?
And then I said, "Yeah, I think so." And
then I had a lot of time to design a
diamond ray
course. And uh so we did it when I got
out of retreat uh we started seven years
of diamond way courses.
And that's I think the total pages is 30
or 40,000 pages of translations
uh for the two for the two courses and
it took 14 years. Uh and uh the problem
is everybody gets to be an old person by
the time you finish. So no, I'm just
kidding. and and I felt uh happy about
it and I I really sincerely believe that
that Diamond Way course the 18
courses is uh the best in history in in
the history because uh Diamond Way was
all broken up uh by many historical
problems and uh it was taught in by
different people in different parts of
the world And no one ever put it
together, put it all together. Uh so
uh I was really happy to do that. I
attended one of the two tantric colleges
uh in the Tibetan Trent. There's two
Gu. My teacher was the administrator of
Guay and uh before he left before he ran
away. So, uh, I was there debating when
they opened their debate ground. Uh,
and,
uh, I was, I thought we could do a
better course. I thought we could do a
more thorough course and a deeper
course, uh, in Diamond Ray. And uh so I
I spent almost those three years in
retreat uh designing a course and
thinking about a course and then uh we
did
it and then uh put people into
three-year retreat and we had a lot of
trouble. It was hard. Uh the courses
were hard. uh this place, you know, you
have roads and you have a cafeteria and
and you have toilets and we had rocks
and
uh it was not easy and but you know,
everyone worked hard and they did a good
job and 30 people or 30 something people
built their own cabin and uh they
donated it to Diamond Mountain when they
finished. Uh, is anybody here from the
three-year retreat? Is there anybody
there? You want to stand up? You
[Applause]
guys and that all was possible because
of Rob Russer. And I'd like him just
[Applause]
Um then uh I I uh did I threaten or I
told my students
um that I didn't that I felt it would be
better if they taught the Diamond Way
courses after me because I thought it
would force them to uh to be diamond
teachers. You know what I mean? So if I
teach then people sometimes don't come
to their course. So I I said I wasn't
going to teach Diamond Way again. And I
and uh I kept that promise
for I don't know 18 years and uh to
almost 20 years. And then uh I'm very
very happy with how they're teaching
Diamond Way. uh John, Connie, Ellie,
other people uh all teaching yay
teaching very nice and and I'm very
proud of that and uh I feel a little
jealous sometimes uh because I don't get
to teach with them and yeah it's okay
but uh I I want to say those who are
teaching Diamond Way from the first
Diamond Way group
uh I'm really really happy and sakme and
David are teaching and and uh I'm really
really happy with that and I feel very
content with that and uh you know they
don't really need me to do the 18
courses and uh I don't have time anyway
tell you the truth we have 42
organizations uh and I'm I'm just
uh I just got back from uh you know 30
day tour. My wife is a little excited
about
that and that's probably my
granddaughter.
Uh but uh my life is very very hard. You
know, I was in Dunong a few days ago,
then I was in Kyoto, then I was in
Hongjo, and then I don't remember before
that. Uh but uh it's it's very very uh
stressful, but I don't feel stressed. I
feel happy. But uh but I can't do more.
I can't do I there's no uh hours left to
do that. So my health is okay. I I don't
have any pain or anything like that. I
have kidney what do you call it? Uh
disease which is a thing that gets worse
every year. And it's called silent. You
don't feel anything. It just gets worse
every year. And so I don't have
unlimited time. uh I I would say I have
maybe I don't know uh but
uh you know I don't have time to I don't
have extra time to spend you know what I
mean I have to do the things I have to
do and uh more than other people I see
the impermanence of life and I see it's
not endless and I can't uh waste time
and I
can't I can't use my time uh I have to
be very smart how I use my turn. Uh
so then a few people good people asked
me to teach them diamond way privately
and I started with a few people. I tried
to do the 18 courses with them and it
just didn't work out. You know it was
just impossible for me to go through.
The homeworks were insane. I don't know
who wrote them,
but but uh they're like crazy. And uh
you know, it's like crazy. And so I
those all failed. We all stopped. Uh I
didn't continue them. And then
uh you a group in uh when I was in
Kyoto, a group, somebody invited me to
dinner in a restaurant, and I never say
yes because I'm too busy. And then I
said, "Yeah, okay. I if I have time,
I'll drop by." And I made a mistake and
I dropped by. And uh they were just
finishing dinner and it was some 30
students and they said they some guy sat
across from me and looked at me and
said, "Can you teach us diamond way?"
And I said, "Yes."
And then I was like, wait, you know, and
uh and but it was a special group of
people that I have worked with for I
don't know, eight years or something.
And I felt I felt like they I could do
something for them. I could do something
special for them. So I've been doing
that uh lightly like I don't know one
day every two months or something. And
uh and then they asked me could I do
another diamond way for ACI and uh I I'm
happy to try I I I'm hungry to teach
Diamond Ray and I enjoy teaching Diamond
Ray and I believe in Diamond Ray and um
you know it just seems like the right
time
uh to do to do it, you know, and so I I
I just said yes right away and
um And I'm I'm happy to do it. I don't
think I
can. I used to know all the students
personally. I used to interview every
single student. There's like 200,000
students now. And people don't
understand that. People say, "Gisha, I
just got to talk to you for an hour."
And I'm like, "You multiply 200,000
times one and then divide by, you know."
And they're like, "Yeah, but I need an
hour." And then I'm like, you know, I
just don't have that uh time. I can't do
that any I can't interview everyone any
anymore. And I can't uh say you should
come and you shouldn't come. How how do
I know? You know, I see you once every
few months or something and I just see
your face. I get a flower and then
I I can't uh do this kind of very tough
thing that I did uh how many years ago I
did 32 years ago. I can't do that. It's
got too many people now. And many people
I believe are ready for Diamond Ray. And
it would be nice, it would be fun to do
Diamond Ray together. And I think a lot
of people would benefit, you know. So, I
I kind of uh that's my opinion and um
I'm sorry for you older people who had
to work so hard in the old days and uh
you can yell at me later. Uh but I'd
like to have some fun and and talk about
Diamond We as your
grandma. And uh you know, let's do that.
And uh there's some requirements. I'm
not going to go through them. They put
me to sleep.
Uh you can talk to Tim. Tim, we we we me
and Tim worked them out. There's not
much requirements, you know. Uh you have
to do what the tradition is, the lineage
is. You have to follow that. And we
built it that way. But it's a lot easier
than it was 30 something years ago.
Okay. And um that's also refi and I just
finished a course this week or we're in
the middle uh where we changed the seim
course. We we allow people to do it over
a month instead of in in 10 days or
something. And then uh I taught some
classes this week uh online for
seim step. I'm not supposed to say
flex. if you had to remember all the
acronyms that I have to remember. People
come like you got ALS because you're
doing DCI with the
SEIM and I'm like I don't know you.
Okay. Yeah, I'm all
overwhelmed. Uh right, JB YSI. Uh so
anyway
uh we we changed the format so that um
we want we wondered what would happen if
people didn't have to ask their boss for
two weeks off and uh suddenly we got a a
whole different group of people
uh who were afraid afraid to get fired.
So they it we're doing two hours in the
morning and an hour in the evening or
something like that and it was a lot
easier and I saw that there were some
nice people who who couldn't come to the
more strict time zones you know and and
I thought wow we should try that. So
anyway I'm happy to do this and I don't
expect you to come to wherever I am
three or four times a year. I I don't
expect that. I know it's not possible.
In a way, the people who do it, they get
broke and then they sleep on people's
couches and everyone gets upset and you
know,
so let's just in English we say muddle
on. Let's try let's see how we do. Okay?
And I'm happy to I'm I'm happy to make
it easier instead of harder for you.
Okay? Because I don't know how many
times I can do this. Sorry, I I'm kind
of feeling in the mood to do it. Okay.
So, I'll make it easy as as easy as I
can. And but then you have to
be, you know, pay attention to the rules
they make and and be serious. And I
don't also don't expect 2,000 people to
stay. If I do my job, there'll be 20
people here uh in a couple months. No
more. But I I know it's not going to be
2,000 people, but anyway, you're welcome
to try
and I I enjoy Diamond Way. I enjoy
teaching. I I think we're going to have
a lot of fun, okay? And uh so just relax
and and enjoy. And and I'm I'm happy to
do it with you. And it's a special
blessing from a different time in my
life. So I'm happy to see you here. And
next life I'll learn everybody's name.
Okay. Okay. Uh first thing we wanted to
do Timothy was
to embarrass Gibson
Chun. He's easily embarrassed. Where are
you? Can you stand up? He's trying to
raise his hand. Yeah. So
[Applause]
So he's one of the 12 mix nut
translators and um to obviously to enter
diamond ray is traditional to study uh
lam rim or the steps of the path
together and
uh you know I was thinking about a
diamond And I was thinking about a l
room rim that would be very appropriate
for this kind of
um friendly group or something, you
know, like new kind of diamond ring. And
I I thought it would be nice to have
a kind of a
special steps of the path just for you
guys. So me and Gibson have been working
on this book for a while and we finished
it. Uh and then we gave it to Anatol who
checks these
things and then we gave it to Rosa who
prints these
things. And does everybody get one
today? Yeah. Let's go.
Uh yeah, if you're here, you get one in
person. Okay.
[Music]
[Applause]
Uh and it's free. If anyone tries to
charge you, tell them to ask
me. Okay. Rosa will figure out the
finances later. That's my mantra with
[Music]
her. All right.
And uh it's a beautiful piece of work.
Okay. Can I see one? I haven't seen one.
Not
bad. Gibson, will you sign it for
me? Nice. I like the smell of a new
fresh boot.
Uh so um this is part of a series of
books that I started uh 30 years ago and
it's called classics of middle
Asia and uh the idea was
to make some books that you could carry
in your purse or you could carry in your
goodn night book club over bed.
overnight bag, carry bag and
uh so that's the idea and we started
this series of translations
uh 30 years
ago and I was on a very terrible bus
ride with my teacher
uh in India uh overnight bus ride with
wooden
seats and Uh it was it was one of the
worst nights of my life. And
uh then we got off the bus to to to do
diarrhea in the
field. I picked a special leaf cuz it
looked like it I didn't have any more
toilet paper and uh turned out to have
little needles on the bottom of it. And
I had an exciting
time and riding on the wooden seat with
the needles getting pushed in and uh
kind of gooey. No. And
uh we got off and
uh there was this guy, I don't know,
some westerner came up to us and and
he's holding one of these books from
this series in his hand and he says,
"Uh, I read this every day. I carry it
everywhere because it's so nice to carry
and uh it changed my life and thank you
so much." And that was like, wow, that's
worth the diarrhea. So,
um anyway, uh we tried to choose a book
that would be easy and easy to carry
around. Uh the other thing about this
book,
uh it's called Song of My Spiritual
Life. Okay. Uh saying
yamgore. Yam means uh well gore means uh
a song a spiritual song and the most
famous gore is the is the gore gorboom
uh which is the 100,000 songs of Millera
Millera lived about 800 years ago in in
Tibet and he's he was a normal business
person or something and then he at the
age of 50 he started diamond way and uh
I think he's a good example for us. Uh
he started diamond way he became a great
meditator and then he started writing uh
songs poetry beautiful poetry called
gore gore and uh gore means a song a
spiritual song and um the English
translation has an interesting history
there was a Chinese Garmas Cece Chung
who uh went to Tibet when in the
1930s or 40s or something like that and
anyway he ended up at Princeton
University as a professor of Buddhism
and he translated
Miller's songs and I missed him. I I got
there just after him. I got him the year
he died. I came the next year and then
um so anyway these songs are very very
famous. His translation is very famous
and uh so these are
similar gore. Okay, gore means a song.
Uh and then is interesting because nyam
means
uh experience. Yam
yamyong in spoken to them. Say
yamyong. Yamyong. It has a nice ring to
it, right? Yamyong means
uh yong uh it means uh personal
experience. Okay. It means
uh you know inner life and the person's
inner life and their personal
experience. So it's very uh Son
Karpa who you know I'm I spent my whole
life translating these books you know
maybe almost 50 years or so every
morning I spend six hours five hours for
a long time and uh I'm working on one of
his books now I think we've done about
3,000 pages of Sukapa in the last year.
He's unbelievable. He's he's the
greatest and I don't
feel shy to say it. He's he's No one
came close to him in history. Uh he's
unbelievable. He he's beyond and but he
never talks about himself. And maybe
that's maybe those two things come
together. you know, he's uh he's so
focused on what Neargina wanted to say
that he he doesn't talk
about never. I I can't recall ever
anywhere. Um he wrote the greatest book
in Tibetan history, uh the LM temo, the
great lman. And he doesn't mention
himself once. I think at the end of the
book he says, "My name's or something.
See you later." you
know, but uh in this book, and that's
why Gibson and I decided to work on it,
he he says, "I'm going to share with you
my personal life, and I'm going to tell
you how I went into Diamond Way. You
know, how what did I do to get ready for
Diamond Way?" And uh his Diamond Way
writings are the greatest. Okay. I was
uh Mr. Bin contacted me from Vietnam
like 10 years ago.
And he said, "Gishla, we don't have much
diamond way here and people don't feel
comfortable with it. People are not sure
if it's real or you know." And then I
said, "Uh, I sent him the To<unk>hoku
catalog
uh took university's catalog of the
scriptures, which is uh 4,600 books.
They are in To<unk>hoku. I went and saw
them. Uh there's third there's uh how
many
There's 3700 commentaries and 990
sutras and and that's the that's
Buddhism. That is Buddhism, you know.
And
uh so I I had played a game with Mr.
Bid. I said, "How many of those are
tantras? How many are diamond ray?" And
he said, "I don't know. How would I
know?" And I said, "I'm can I send them
to you?" And he's like, "Yeah, you send
it to me." you know and then I it's
exactly
how okay it's like in from the from the
ka from the ancient sutras it's it's
it's 500 of the 990 books are tantra or
diamond ray you know so to say it's not
real or Buddha didn't teach it or
something like that is ridiculous it's
it's just if you understand anything
about Buddhism you're like ah you
It's it's crazy. You know, Buddha spent
half his time teaching diamond and and
it's amazing and it's beautiful and it's
wonderful and it's clean and there's no
weird stuff. Okay? Uh it's not weird. We
don't kill chickens. We don't have sex
in the temple. If you're expecting that,
you're you're gonna have to go somewhere
else. Okay? I I don't have any
recommendations but um but uh but it's
very very beautiful and and sweet and
kind and compassionate and wonderful and
happy and okay it's not I was in
Uruguay. I went to Ponta Deesta
uh to teach a soccer team professional
soccer team. You know I thought it was
going to be messy. John, you know that
he does that all the time. I mean, he
goes and teaches large groups around the
world
and he he you know, he just shows up and
suddenly it's the New York Jets or
something. I don't have this problem.
And uh but it was a bunch of soccer
players and they're all drunk. Some guy
fell in the pool. We had he almost
drowned and uh but we stayed until they
stayed until three in the morning and we
had a beautiful conversation. We had a
beautiful meeting and they couldn't stop
talking about the ideas and it was so
beautiful and uh the next morning I I
went back to the airport. you have to
fly over the river back to Rio de
Janeiro and
um and uh I was in the airport and I saw
a big uh sign that said Tantra, you
know, and I'm like whoa in
Uruguay, you know, and I went over there
and it was terrible. It was a terrible,
terrible book. Something really dirty
and strange and I was so disappointed. I
felt so sad that this kind of thing had
come to Latin America, you know, and and
this is how people think of it. And I
was very sad and I'll never forget it,
you know. I was just walking through the
airport with some of the soccer players,
you know, and it was so it was
so sick, you know, and that's like, wow,
that's bad, you know. So, yeah, it's not
like that at all. Okay. Diamond Way
is beautiful, fun. It's like being
sitting with your
grandmother. Okay. And it's it's very
very sweet. Okay.
Uh so I wanted to talk about I'm going
to go through uh I have a thing called a
flow document which is how I teach
nowadays in um it took me I don't know
50 years to to in to to come to here. I
came to a way of teaching where I have
uh a document that I prepare. I meditate
on the teaching
maybe for a couple weeks or something
like that. Uh so my morning practice I
maybe I'll meditate on these classes two
weeks ago and I'll get ready for the
class and I'll I'll meditate on it and
the
meditation is based on images. I use uh
pictures uh to remember what I'm going
to teach. And I find pictures are more
powerful than
words. And I I think it's very um
fascinating to have a language like
Chinese where you use pictures as your
words. And I think there's something
cool about there's something important
about that. Uh but anyway, I do a I do a
flow dog and we're going to talk more
about that uh especially in the next
class today. Uh because I want to talk
to you about do learning how to do it
yourself uh when you teach especially.
Okay. Uh so I use pictures and and they
help me ground my talk. They help me go
through the talk. They deepen my
understanding of the talk. So, I'm going
to follow these pictures and it also
helps keep grandpa on track. Old people
like to tell stories and then suddenly
it's the end of the class and you didn't
learn anything
maybe. Okay, next picture we're going to
try. Is it Brian or who do I Francisco?
Who do I yell at?
Fernando. Let's do the la last Oh, last
picture. first picture. Yeah. Okay. So,
um again, this is how we're going to
start. Uh my stepson painted Sonappa. Uh
he's a very great painter and uh he
should be a painter. I don't know why
he's running this little cafe, but uh
he's he's really really good. He had a
one night show. He made $14,000 last
week.
and but he wants to make coffee all day.
So I don't know but um it's a beautiful
uh painting and uh and tried
to get the feeling of
some finally willing to talk about his
personal life and finally willing to
give us some trade secrets. Uh what what
to meditate about. Okay. So, yamgore.
Okay. Nyamgore.
Um, there's a tradition that sappa is
mandushri. And as I get
older, couple things happened to me. I I
uh I used to get confused by the
Sanskrit names. You know, there were
some terrible ones. I can't remember.
you know, sati
just I felt uh I felt like an
outsider because it was all a foreign
language and I I I studied in India. I I
I started with that and um and I was
there for many years uh total and
uh and as I get older I I think um it's
not so important what their name is and
I I don't think it's so important to use
their to call Manushi or or Maitraa or
people get confused what's the
difference do I have to be Indian to
study this you know do do I have to
remember his name to get to know him you
know and and I just feel sort of as I
get older and as I learn more and as I
master all the languages more I think
they are less important you know to to
call him Mjushi or call him so kappa
forget it Mr. onion field, you know,
where'd that come
from? Like I keep trying to think of
Onion Field in a tantric way and I still
haven't figured it out, you know, like
he smells sweet, you know? I don't know.
And uh so anyway, what I wanted to say
is
uh first I think Jay Rimple, Tibetans
call him J Rimpache. They rarely call
him. J Ramputain means
precious lord or something jewel Mr.
Jewel or something like that. Okay. And
uh he's supposed to be
mandushri and uh then I feel
guilty. Uh my teacher says don't forget
soap is mandushri you know and I'm like
I forget what's
mandushri and you know he says the god
of wisdom you know and I'm like what do
you mean god? Did he make the world or
no? And then I gets all confused, you
know, and uh
and and then I I just didn't feel very
comfortable with the whole thing, you
know, am I supposed to have a big hat to
be a good person or, you know, do I have
to have a foreign name uh to be a good
person? And then at this
stage, you know, and I
I there's probably nobody alive who has
worked harder on the scriptures. I think
so. And who who has translated more of
them, who understands them? And I I want
to say
uh the whole question of Saba boils down
to when you look at the cover of the
book, when you see the first image here,
okay? And you're going to get lots of
images in the next I don't know how many
years it's going to take. Okay?
Uh but when you look at the
picture, what I want you to do, you
know, and carry the book around with you
and look at it, open it every morning or
open it at night. It's a good luck
thing. Okay? Just say, "I had a lousy
day." Okay? And I'm grumpy. Okay? And
I'm going to bed. Okay? Read read a few
sentences. Shut up and read a few
sentences and then go to sleep. I didn't
understand anything Gisha. That's the
point. It's something new, something
that's going to change you. Okay. So,
what I want to say in the first class
and I'll probably say it in the last
class. Okay. The first thing Gishla said
in the new diamond ray class is uh is he
a
Buddha? Is he the Buddha? Is he the
Buddha of wisdom? Is he Mushouchri? you
know and I I want to say my opinion okay
uh I have not met him directly okay in
my meditations in my experiences I have
not met him directly
um and
uh according to diamond way the most
important teaching of diamond way okay
I'll tell you tonight in case we all die
uh is
that there's there's a joke there's
inside Buddhist joke. Uh how many
Buddhists are in the audience today? you
know, and there's like I don't know two
I mean Kiri and you know Sushumna for
sure those two like you know who knows I
don't know you know and
then by tradition according to a diamond
way
uh what is it what's that call it done
the thing
Connie no
done well how's The opening lines of
hat
anyway they have killed death with the
stick. You know there are the opening
lines of hat
yoga say that there are people walking
around among us
uh who are Buddhists they're enlightened
they killed death. Kala danda they
killed death. They don't have to die and
they're just walking around all the
time. And uh what else they going to do?
I don't know, you know. So,
uh according to the way I like to
present it, we were in Dun Huang last
week. Okay. Dun Huang is on the edge of
the Gobi Desert. There's 700
medication meditation caves.
700 meditation caves were dug out of the
cliffs there. At any given time a
thousand years ago, there was a thousand
people meditating in caves. Sorry, 700.
I guess some of them had friends and uh
and they would practice there this
stuff, you know. And then uh in 1900 on
June 25th
uh that the rumor is that some monk was
smoking and he saw the air draft draft
of air coming out of a crack and they
broke the wall and they found uh
60,000 books, 60,000 manuscripts and
it's like unbelievable, you know. It's
just it's unbelievable. So, we I've been
there a couple times now and uh they
found the oldest book in the world
there. They found the diamond cutter
sutra there. It's the oldest printed
book in the world with a date which is
867. I don't know something like that.
867 something like that. So anyway,
uh the oldest book in the world was
found in in these caves, you know, and
we went there and we
were, you know, having just feeling our
way there and and you can feel the we
had a program there, innovation retreat
program, and it was unbelievable and the
the feeling of the Gobi Desert, the sand
dunes and everything, it's like
unbelievable. we should go there
sometime again. And we had this amazing
amazing time and
then I had to go to the hospital for
some kind of uh little problem. And um
they found out I was a translator and
they gave me this suite with with the
director and assistant directors and you
know was they said oh you're a
translator you know you get the it's not
like America
okay in America they say
what is that
like so anyway uh think about the
diamond cutter sutra if if it is the
most printed book in history. Okay. It
beats the Bible by as far as printing,
it's probably the sales were double or
something, you know, to be honest. I
mean, I'm loyal to the Bible. I like it.
I grew up with it. But diamond cutter
is about twice. The sales are about
twice and it's been printed for a
hundred generations, you know, and you
can go to Den Huang and people still
give you a special room if you can
translate it. you know, and uh you know,
why did it survive so long? You know,
why did it why did it last so long? John
and me wrote a book. He wrote a book. I
help I I helped
uh you know, with the grammar and stuff
because he's a pilot. But um but I was
uh it got very famous. The book got very
famous. And I I was at the airport in
Phoenix and I saw I saw a hundred copies
on the wall and I was like, "Yeah, you
know, it's a bestseller, you know, and
uh and I was running to the plane and I
didn't with Scott or and I I didn't have
time to buy it and I thought, well,
we're going to be back in a week. I'll
buy it then, you know, and then uh so we
came back and and I went to the
bookstore and and it's gone." And I
said, "Where's that book by that famous
Blue Angels guy?" And they're like, "Oh,
we only keep books here for a week." And
I'm like, "What?" And he said, "Yeah,
you know, we sell them for a week and
then we sell the next week, you know."
And I'm like, "Well, I really wanted a
copy." And they said, "Well, you you'll
have to order it online or something,
you know." I'm like, "Okay." What I mean
to say is that the Diamond Cutter
Sutra has been
reprinted in the bookstore called the
world
for two and a half thousand years for a
hundred generations. Okay? And the
purpose of that book is to help you
touch the diamond world to see emptiness
directly. Okay? And that's all it's used
for. It it you can't use it for much
else.
uh doesn't have any recipes, nothing.
uh and
uh people have passed it on to their
kids for a 100 generations for two and a
half thousand years which means to
me there's a possibility that it
works because you don't pass on a book
if it didn't if you're going to choose
one book to give to your kids in ancient
times which is expensive books in those
days if you had a library, you have to
be wealthy. You know, there were no
public libraries and people spent the
money and the time to print a diamond
cutter and hand it to their kids and
say, "You if you don't ever read
anything else, read this." And what
happened was
uh it must have worked. I say logically,
okay, on my in my opinion,
logically, you don't pass on a book if
it doesn't work. You see what I mean?
They uh found a clay tablet Babylonian
recently like 20 years ago and it's the
oldest writing in the history and it's
clay uh it's a clay tablet and it has
Babylonian letters on it and they found
it and they they worked on the
translation. They worked and worked and
worked, you know, and then
they they figured out what it says. It
says, "I sold a horse to this guy and he
didn't pay me and I want to take him to
court and if you can help me sue the
guy, you can have half the horse." And
you
know, this the oldest printed thing in
the world, you know, and what I'm saying
is that things survive when they're
important and when they work, which
means, okay, you
ready? that
uh somebody must have gotten enlightened
by all those sutras and stuff. John
Brady, this cool
guy is uh his target is
300,000 ancient books. Okay, his target
he has finished 19,000. He has finished
80 million
words. Yay.
[Applause]
He's uh 7% done. So, he has to live
another Never mind.
Uh but
uh you know there's there's all these
books. Why do they survive?
Somebody used them and they worked for
somebody which means that logically not
not a religious not not
religiously
logically there's Buddhas walking around
otherwise the book would have would have
been stored with the Babylonian clay
tablet you know you see what I mean why
would it be printed over and over and
over again if it didn't work you know So
logically there's Buddhists walking
around. Logically, okay, you ready? It's
possible that this guy is a
Buddha. And logically, it's possible
that he's not. Okay? And I and I think
that's
why Buddhists, real Buddhists, spend 10
10 to 20% of their time studying logic.
Okay?
Logically, he could be a Buddha. You
can't say he's not. Can you say he's
not? Can you anyone in this room say
he's not a Buddha? That he's not
Majushi. It's a the god of wisdom. Can
you say for sure? And then everybody's
like, I don't know. Even the Buddhists
in the room are faking it and saying, I
don't know. You know and then now on the
other hand can you say logically that he
is a
Buddha? No you cannot. I don't accept
it. I I don't say so. I don't think it's
logical. I I don't think you can say
he's a Buddha. You don't know. Okay.
There's a lot of indications that he
might be. You know, nobody else could
write. In my opinion, it'd be difficult
to write it if you're not a guru. But
um my first Diamond Way class, which you
will never forget, even if you never
come
back, which I'm ready for, that's okay.
Uh I don't mind. The the one thing
you'll hear from me in the first Diamond
Way class is that you can't say he's
not and you cannot say he
is. And that's Diamond Way. Okay? And if
you never hear anything else from me
about Diamond Way, if we all get blown
up tonight by all our tariffs,
uh, you heard that. You heard that from
me. Okay. And you I don't think you can
prove it's wrong. You know, there there
could be
Buddhists. The person sitting next to
you right now could be a
Buddha. And it's possible that they're
not also. And and I can't say I cannot
honestly say, okay, got it. Uh I can
tell you one thing, okay, from personal
experience and I'm an old man and I
don't care if you don't believe me. Uh I
saw emptiness directly. I spent my life
trying to teach it to people. I don't
know anyone else in the world who did.
Uh but I cannot prove it to you. I can
discuss it with you. I can share my
experiences. I cannot prove it to you.
and and uh and you cannot say for sure
that I have uh but I know what it feels
like to walk around the whole world for
almost
40 for 50 years and and look at people
and know they don't know who I am. You
see what I mean? Like I meet people on
the plane and they say, "What do you
do?" And I say, "Forget it." I if I try
to explain, you won't believe me anyway.
You know, I learned a long time ago. I
don't talk on the plane anymore. Uh I
just watch the movies. No, but you know
the they I know what it feels like to be
something. I know what it feels like to
have been to every planet in the
universe. I know what that is. I've been
there. Uh, but I also know what it feels
like to walk around the world and no one
sees that. No one can see it. I know
what it feels like, you know, and I'm
okay with it. I have fun. I still have
pastries and don't don't tell my wife.
Yesterday, I stopped at the health food
place, Arcadia
Farms, and I found a a walnut pastry.
So anyway, uh I know what it feels like
to to be
anonymous at a different level. You see
what I mean? And I'm okay. I I don't
mean I'm upset or you don't have to rush
up to me after class and say, "I'm sorry
I treated you like a schmuck." Uh that's
okay. I don't mind at all. But I know
what it feels like uh to to I can sit
here and I I have seen every planet. I
have been there personally. I have met
every person who's alive in the universe
and I I have done that. But I know what
it feels like to walk around the world
and nobody knows or or nobody would
believe it anyway and nobody except the
people here would care. Uh but uh what
I'm saying is the the Buddhist in the
room, they probably feel the same way.
You know, they're like, "Yeah, okay. I'm
just here, you know, if I can help you,
I'm available." That's
their job. That's what they do. They
infiltrate groups. They sneak into the
room. They look like normal people. They
act like normal people and then right at
the moment that you need some patience
meditation, they do something to piss
you off.
Uh, okay. Understand? That's tantra.
That's diamond way. Okay. If you're not
a
Buddha, and I have no idea who you are,
uh if you're not a Buddha, you can join
me in the secret Buddha admiration club
and uh doubting who you're sitting next
to in the airplane and, you know, trying
to figure out who they are. And what
happens after years of thinking like
that is you feel sort of peaceful and
happy
and you you've
accepted that there may be a Buddha
sitting next to you and you deal with
it, you know, and when that person is
good to you or that person is mean to
you, you you you turn on your diamond
wave sensibility. You say,
"Well, maybe they're trying to help me
somehow." You have this uh reverse
paranoia. Diamond Way is reverse
paranoia. You know, paranoia. People say
he's trying, everyone hates me.
Everyone's trying to screw me. You know,
they're looking like this at everybody.
Then diamond wave paranoia is like,
"Maybe she's the Buddha. Maybe he's the
Buddha. Oh my god." You know, I'm so
lucky.
Okay, that's time. If you never come
back to this class again
uh and maybe you don't have to
uh just remember that is the whole
diamond ring. Okay, there's nothing
else. I mean in can I say in the first
half of diamond ring? Uh that's that's
the first. So that's that's what am I
supposed to stop him? I just have a
clock. What time does it
stop? At five. Okay, good. Uh, I'll try
to finish. The other reason I do these
pictures is that I know I have to finish
them to get out of the class or else I
didn't give the whole class. Next
picture. Me and uh Rob Russer, we worked
for I don't know how many
years. Uh there was no good uh life
story of Tonkapa. There was no
biography. There were some small
things, you know, in Wikipedia that were
ridiculous and, you know, there was no
information about him. And um I I was
very frustrating to me and uh so here's
the
story and I won't finish all the
pictures.
Uh so I lived in a Mongolian temple in
New Jersey.
for 25 years and my teacher taught me
privately for 25 years and um in
addition to going to the Gisha course
and then uh he would teach
uh he had a small group he he had maybe
on on a normal night he might have 15
people or something 20 people and and
um we didn't have any money at all and
we were broke And
um we were living in this Mongolian
temple and all of the people in the town
were refugees from the Nazi
concentration camps. They jumped over
the fence, you know, and they they were
tough. They were real Mongol warriors
and they were a lot of them were messed
up. There's a lot of drug addicts and
alcohol and it was a hard hard time. uh
and and he was an he was a visiting uh
monk. He he was supposed to serve them.
He didn't speak their language, you
know, and and it was a hard time for
both of us. So, but anyway, I snuck in.
I helped him. He taught me for free,
whatever. And uh then he would teach in
the summertime. he would have a special
retreat and everyone he ever met would
come and we'd have like 30 40 people and
um we'd sit in this big Mongolian temple
and it was bitterly uncomfortably uh it
was New Jersey hot. Arizona hot is
cool. New Jersey hot is miserable. It
feels like being in a Japanese sweat
lodge. No, you're just sweating. It's
all wet. It's like Kyoto in August or
something. We don't go there. Uh but uh
it's uncomfortable. And uh so by the
way, Kyoto is my second home, but don't
tell my wife.
Um and it's my favorite place to be in
the world, maybe physically. Uh but
anyway, uh so I I was uh we would sit
there and cook and then he'd we had this
steeple, you know, and it had windows at
the top and he'd say, "You climb up
there and open the windows and it's very
dangerous. It's triple ladder and I was
scared out of my mind to go up there."
And one day I almost fell. I think I
fell and I think Buddha pushed me back
or something. No, I was like this and
then I was like this and I was like,
"What just happened?" You know, and it
was u So anyway, I'm up there and I'm
I'm scared to death and I'm looking
through the ladder and I can't quite
reach the window and there's paintings
all around me. There's paintings way way
up there and I'm looking at them and I'm
like, "Wow, these are cool." And they
had a little writing on them.
And they use a single
horsehair, what do you call horsetail
hair to paint the letters. A single
hair. And they sit there for like three
years to make one tanka to make one
painting. And they write Sonkapa's life
story. And you can't see the writing
from down below. you have to your llama
has to set you up to
die and then you earn this right you
know and I was like wow you know and I
went down and I I went to my llama's
room I said there's writing on those
paintings and he said I know and uh I I
said why you never told me he goes oh
that's called son getu that's the
80 major events of sonap's life and
there's 15 paintings
very very rare, extremely rare. Uh
there's only a few sets in the
world. And anyway, so me and Rob Russer,
we worked on them for many years and we
finished and we we did a book. We we
wrote a book called King of the Dharma
and it's has all the paintings and we
found the original John Brady found the
original manuscript
uh of how to paint it and what to write
on the painting and it was a big big
deal. It was like unbelievable. So we
you can read his life story in pictures
which is always easier. You don't have
to be like Kiri and and read the 200
books of Harry Potter in the same week.
Okay? You can
uh you can get a good picture of his
life. So me and Rob I I started to go to
museums and teach the paintings. I was
at the National Museum of Argentina.
I was teaching these paintings and um
then I asked Rob, could we make some
posters to put around the room, you
know? So we identified
12 themes of Sonapa's life, 12 roles
that he played in his life. And then we
made posters. He and I made posters. And
um I thought we would
uh show you the posters during this
Diamond Way
classes and then uh we'll give you the
posters. I mean I don't know if I can
afford it but you might have to help me
to pay for it but we'll give you one by
one. We'll explain the poster. Each
poster has
a each poster has one of the important
parts of Tonkapa's life. for
example, uh he thought it was important
to learn to sing and to learn to dance.
And people don't know that. People don't
know that it's it's a diamond way
practice. And he he was doing all these
special dances. I learned some of them
in Mongolia and uh singing these special
songs, you know, and it's it's amazing
stuff like that. Okay. So you'll get a
poster once every session like every
time we meet together. We will meet
together on the alarm room four times a
year. I think it will take six sessions.
I think it will take a year and a half.
Okay. Then we'll start diamond way.
Haha. No, my joke. It's an inside joke.
The whole lament classes will be diamond
way. probably will finish dying way by
the time we finish the preparation for
Dway. That's my secret plan. No, don't
worry. I'll give you more.
Um, but my idea is if something happens
with my health, I want to make sure you
get all the important stuff. Okay? And u
so I'm not going to hide it for the
first year and a half. I will dump it on
you for a year and a half and then after
a year and a half we'll start real
diamond way and you'll say that's
exactly what you taught from last year.
I'm used to it. It's okay. Okay. So
anyway, this book will be important for
you. Okay. And uh try to get a copy.
Rosa has all it's it's on uh what do you
call Diamond Cutter Press website.
Recently Rob and me worked on a
paperback because the old one was really
expensive and we the income from that
book we give it to the temple where they
are keeping the posters. Okay. So we
just give it all to them and they depend
on it. Uh so we've done that for many
years now almost 20 years. Okay. They
came here some of some of them came you
you met them. Yeah you know. Okay.
Uh here's the most important thing in
this class uh from Gibson's new book and
thank you Gibson and it's a beautiful
book. Uh yeah
[Applause]
[Music]
uh the most important two verses okay in
the whole book it's a refrain. It means
he keeps repeating every time. Who is
that? It's not my boss. No, it's my male
clinic. Uh, every every time he goes
through an important
idea of Diamond Way, he says the same
two lines and Gibson's gonna recite
[Music]
them. You got a microphone, you guys.
Hi, Brian.
You got to really act it up.
Okay, good.
[Music]
Yay.
Uh, here's the He memorized it. Uh,
here's the English. I the deep
practitioner. What's the Sanskrit for
deep practitioner? Yo, yogi. Well, he
calls himself a yogi. This is the only
book where he calls himself a yogi. I
the yogi meaning high practitioner, deep
practitioner, uh have accomplished my
practice this
way. If you hope for freedom, you should
do the same. Okay? And that's that's the
refrain that's over and over in this
book. You will see the same two lines
after every instruction page. He says,
"Hey, you guys, that's what I did. Look
at me. You should do that." You know,
and it's very very again, he doesn't
talk like that ever. Never. He never
claims to be a a Buddha. He never claims
to be an Arya. He He just teaches you
how to do it. Okay? But in this book, he
comes out of the closet. Okay? And he's
he's like, "That's what I did. Maybe you
want to do that. Okay, that's the
structure of this book. So, don't forget
that line.
[Music]
Okay, right. That's what you guys should
do. All right. Uh there's a
picture. Next
picture. That's Sappa. Okay.
uh he's riding a tiger which is diamond
way and uh during his
lifetime he didn't tell people what he
was doing much almost
never and then after he passed away he
came to his
uh student one of his famous students
Kuj in a dream riding a tiger and he
said you
That's that's what it's all about.
Diamond way is what it's all about, you
know, and riding the tiger is what it's
all about. And we'll talk about that.
We'll talk about riding the tiger. But
this is a uh in Mongolia they keep that
dream very dear. And they they carve
this carving and someone gave me a copy.
Okay.
[Music]
My llama when I became a monk he sewed
the rose. It's very complex. It's very
very like secret how to sew the patches.
And he and he sewed them himself. And he
said, "Get me a sewing machine. You want
to be a monk? Get me a sewing machine."
I'm like, "You don't know how to use a
sewing machine." He says, "You never saw
me use a sewing machine." There's He
used to say, "There's a lot of things
you don't know." I said, "I didn't know
you could use the sewing sewing
machine." He's like, "There's a lot of
things you don't know about me." Anyway,
he made the robes. I wore them for many,
many
years, 20 years, 25 years. Then they
finally they fell apart and uh I was in
threeear retreats. I couldn't I didn't
want to lose the robes. So, I made the
frame for the painting. I sold the frame
uh for the carving. Those are my old
ropes. Okay. Uh, and that's a tree of
retreat
stick, you know, that we used to use to
keep the rattlesnakes out of the
house. Okay. All right. I got four more
minutes. I think we can do it. Next
picture. There's one of the posters.
Okay.
And uh each one has a quotation of some
kind and each one has an instruction
from Jets Cabo. And each of the
paintings or pictures has a story and
I'll teach you this story. Okay? Each
one comes from somewhere. All right?
Like the black and white one.
uh the Americans during World War II
were trying to make contact with the
Chinese army so they could work together
and
uh they they tried to see if they could
fly from India to China which you cannot
because it's too high the the engine
runs out of oxygen but they tried and
they crashed in Tibet uh and
uh do you know Toltoy Russian famous toy
uh most one of the most famous authors
from Russia. His nephew was the
pilot, American pilot and uh he had a
camera and then he took all these
pictures of these secret rituals like he
snuck in and he took all these pictures.
So that's a Diamond Way meeting at Tulk
uh in Tibet in 1940 something and he he
took a picture. He shouldn't take a
picture. He wasn't allowed to take a
picture. There's one monk going like
this and uh so I'll teach you all those
things and I'll I'll share with you the
stories and it's kind of cool. All
right. And they are having a dance. They
are they are dressed for dance. Okay.
And we'll talk about
it. And got you don't have to dance.
Okay. If you're old and your knees are
bad, you can just snap your fingers or
something. Okay. Uh, next
picture. Yeah. I'm sorry for the big
bottom. I I uh I have an AI. I say,
"Show a lady walking up the steps." And
we tried like six times and this is the
best one. You should see the other ones.
Uh anyway, uh we're going to go step by
step. That's what long room means. Okay?
And it's
a very very fun. Okay? It's it's a
certain certain steps you have to you
have to do the same steps. There's
certain steps that Sonappa identified
and the Buddha identified and said,
"Look, don't worry about anything.
There's 10 things you have to do. Just
do these 10 and you'll become a Buddha
and don't don't worry about it. Just
take each step that I ask you to take
and in the end you're going to say,
"Hey, I'm a Buddha." And I'll say, "See,
I told you so."
Okay. Okay. So, that's Lam Rim. And and
uh what's funny is that the L rim
teachings even in this
book don't read the last part without
reading the first part because you're
allowed to teach diamond way in Lumbrin
as as part of the steps of the path
lamin you're allowed to talk about
secret Buddhism diamond way okay she's
already I was already looking at the
last verse
Anyway, there is time to end this book
at the last the last section is about
diamond ring. Okay? And he wants to
share about that, but you have to go
step by step. It's not like you're going
to, you know, lightning's going to hit
you if you look at the back of the book
or and it's not true that you'll never
become a Buddha if you cheat.
uh you know the Buddhists wouldn't give
you the book if they if that was true
because they know you can't control
yourself. So they probably want you to
look at the last page first. Uh but uh
anyway, have fun with it. You can read
any part you want. I don't care if you
read any of it. I'm happy. Okay. Uh and
um that's that's the idea. Just do what
we say in the class. We will be meeting
for a year and a half. You can come
online if you have to. You know, I'd
rather have people with real jobs who
don't come once in a while than lots of
unemployed people who want to sleep on
my couch
uh cuz the cats there full
time. Okay. Anything else?
Yeah, I think we'll start the next one
tomorrow. Yeah, that's a good place to
stop. Okay. And and uh thank you for
coming. Thank you for asking me to
teach. Again, I want to
repeat. If you have your own teachers,
which you should have, and they're
teaching you Diamond Way, which they
should, then keep going. I I don't want
to I'm not a replacement. I'm just
dessert. Okay? So, please study with
your regular teachers. Please study
diamond way with your teachers when they
say you're ready because they know you
and I don't know you
necessarily. And you're very welcome to
come to grandpa's class and I'll just
wander around and talk about
stories and uh it'll make your diamond
way studies more deep and more
beautiful. And you don't have to study
with other teachers if you don't want
to. But if you're if you're in the mood,
uh it's very important. They will give
you detail that I can never give you. I
will never have time to to do all those
courses. Okay? So I think let's do both.
Okay? And that's the best thing. Okay?
All right. I'll see you after a half
hour break. Okay? Thank you.